[Music]
you how not to die I compiled the
healthiest of the so-called green light
Foods into my daily dozen checklist and
encourage people to try to fit them into
their daily routine I made it into a
free app Dr Gregor's daily dozen
available for iPhone and Android so
anyone and everyone can try to check off
all the boxes every day and track their
progress over time as the feedback
poured in from millions of people giving
the app a try two themes of complaints
arose the first was that it was just too
much food there was no way they could
eat all that food in one day in response
I explained that look the daily dozen
was aspirational something to shoot for
just a tool to inspire people to include
some of the healthiest of healthy foods
into their daily diets the vast volume
of food I prescribed was on purpose I
mean I was hoping by encouraging people
to eat so much healthy stuff it would
naturally crowd out some of the less
healthy stuff after checking off 24
servings and the daily dozen there's
only so much room left for a pepperoni
pizza ironically the second major
complaint we got is that it doesn't have
enough calories I had to explain that
the Daily doesn't just represent the
minimum I encourage people to eat not
the maximum and the certainly you know
training athletes requiring thousands
more calories would have to eat much
more um this all got me thinking though
too much food but too few calories
sounds like the perfect weight loss diet
the daily dozen is by definition all
greenl foods all whole plant Foods so
that right there bakes in all 17
ingredients of the ideal weight loss
diet I introduced in my book how not to
diet what about the calorie count a
systematic review of successful weight
loss strategies concluded that given the
metabolic slow and increased appetite
that accompanies weight loss to achieve
significant weight loss calorie counts
may need to drop as low as 1200 calories
a day for women and 1,500 calories a day
for men and what do you know plug in
common foods into each of the categories
in the daily dozen averages about 1,200
calories with the higher calorie food
choices nailing 1,500 calories in the
second half of how not to diet I focus
on things that can further EX accelerate
the loss of body fat regardless of what
you eat which I encapsulated in my 21
tweaks my free Dr Gregor's daily dozen
app had become so popular at that point
that I decided to revamp it with these
new features now if you switch over to
the weight loss setting you can make a
game out of how many fat busting
boosters you can squeeze in every day Al
with your daily dozen check boxes does
this actually help people lose weight
though you don't know until you
put it to the test as part of a master's
thesis in lifestyle medicine at the
Lithuanian University of Health Sciences
a graduate student conducted weight
control and lifestyle change using Dr
Michael Gregor's daily dozen in 21
tweaks does it really work a pilot study
how cool is that a before and after
study with no control so it's really
more like a case series of four Men Four
Women on average obese who are
encouraged to use the app and follow the
daily dozen and 21 tweaks for 4 weeks uh
preceded by a prep phase which included
educational sessions and even a cooking
class Then followed up for a month after
the diet at the end of the 4-we
intervention an average weight loss of
about 15 PBS was achieved along with a
few inches Dro from the waist the two
folks with diabetes lowered their sugars
by about 50 points LDL cholesterol
dropped by 35 points that's the kind of
drop we'd see with a first generation
stattin drug three reached their ideal
range under an LDL of 70 that's really
the most important thing as heart
disease is the leading killer in
Lithuania as it is in the United States
in addition to physical health mental
health appears to improve as well a
month after the study was over the
participants appeared to be able to
retain enough healthy eating habits to
maintain the weight loss and improved
well-being but as they strayed their
cholesterol and blood sugars crept back
up it was so cool to read all the
participants comments they never felt
hungry their taste buds started changing
they even learned to cook a little
oatmeal of course what they were really
happy about was losing all that weight
while experiencing some positive side
effects now obviously a small
uncontrolled study is some super weak
sauce evidence but what it did show is
that it's possible to make a lot of diet
and lifestyle changes at once and if
they're healthy changes they may bring
about some healthy effect Ma
[Music]